Finding Aid for English Language Institute (University of Michigan) Records, 1940-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
English Language Institute (University of Michigan), records 1940-2004
University of Michigan. English Language Institute.
87164 Bimu C262
University of Michigan department responsible in part for the development of materials for the teaching of English as a second language. The English Language Institute records contain correspondence, notes from staff meetings, printed materials, reports, photographs, and administrative records, especially records of South East Asia Regional English Program and the Ford-Japan Project. The records also include files of directors Charles C. Fries and Robert Lado and administrator George E. Luther. Also includes photos of institute staff, students, and activities, including foreign students at the University of Michigan and the institute's South East Asia Regional English Project (1957-1965).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
18.3 linear feet
The records of the English Language Institute (Donor Nos. 3349 and 7050 ) were first donated in 1984. Additions to the collection were given in December 1999 and March 2004
The record group is open without restriction.
The English Language Institute (ELI) was founded by Charles C. Fries in 1941 as the first full-time intensive English Language Institute in the United States, and was in the forefront of English as a Second Language (ESL) teaching and ESL teacher training. ELI's special interest and involvement in language testing began more than fifty years ago with the work of Robert Lado. Since the early 1950s, ELI has been developing and administering various language tests, some designed for use within the University of Michigan and others for use nationally and internationally. By the late 1950s the ELI had international language programs in countries on five continents. One of the most extensive was the Southeast Asian Regional English Project (SEAREP), with a budget of nearly two million dollars under contract to the United States Agency for International Development (AID). During the 1960s and 70s, ELI developed experimental teaching methods, materials, and teacher training programs to aid in the teaching of English as a second or foreign language. Large-scale research and development of teaching materials including textbooks and audio-tapes were produced and marketed through the University of Michigan Press.
In 1986, the ELI adopted a new mission: to provide a full range of courses in English for Academic Purposes (EAP) for non-native speaking students, staff, visiting scholars, and faculty at the University of Michigan and to carry out relevant research. The new courses were designed to help non-native speakers enhance their linguistic and communicative skills to become effective, fully participating members of the academic community both during their campus career and beyond. In support of this new mission in the university, the ELI has engaged in research and development across a number of key areas, including ESP instruction and particularly task-based instruction, applied to discourse analysis, language assessment, applications of audio and video technology within language instruction, and adult second language acquisition.
At present ELI has forged links with the world, providing research facilities and consultation for visiting scholars from China, Tadzhikistan, South Africa, Sweden, and Brazil, to name a few. The Morley Scholarship Fund, established under director John Swales, has provided financial support for several researchers. The testing program has also expanded from two to three overseas testing operations, and on campus the ELI offers thirty courses at the graduate and undergraduate level for students, researchers, visiting scholars, and university staff in a variety of subjects. Other offerings include International Graduate Student Instructor spring and summer workshops for LS&A and Engineering, speaking and writing clinics, and pre-sessional summer programs in EAP: English for Business Studies, and English for Legal Studies. The ELI website can be found at: http://www.lsa.umich.edu/eli/.
English Language Institute Directors
1941-1956 Charles Carpenter Fries
1956-1960 Robert Lado
1960-1962 A.H. Marckwardt, Acting Director and Director
1963-1964 E.M. Anthony, Acting Director
1964-1975 J.C. Catford, Director
1976 H.D. Brown, Acting Director
1976-1977 Ken Pike, Director
1977-1982 L. Selinker
1982-1984 E. Rabkin, Interim Director
1984-2002 John Swales, Acting Director and Director
2002- Diane Larsen-Freeman
The records of the English Language Institute of The University of Michigan encompass the period, 1940-2004, and contain 11 series: Correspondence; C.C. Fries Correspondence; Books; Manuscripts and Publications; Scrapbooks; Project Files; Administrative Files; South East Asia Regional English Project (SEAREP); Ford-Japan Project; Publications; and Photographs. The bulk of the collection deals with routine business such as student requests for admission, inquiries from throughout the world regarding the operation of the Institute, requests for linguistic materials available from the Institute, and staff meeting minutes. There is an abundance of information on the relationship between the English Language Institute, its staff and similar institutions both at the University of Michigan and elsewhere; including the University of Michigan International Center, the Civil Aeronautics Administration, the English Language Institute in Mexico, the Ford Foundation, the Inter-American Educational Foundation, the Kellogg Foundation, the Linguistic Institute, Rockefeller Foundation, and the U.S. Office of Education. Also in the collection are extensive files of directors Charles C. Fries and Robert Lado and administrator George E. Luther.
Subjects:
Asia, Southeastern.; English language--Study and teaching--Foreign speakers.; Language and languages.; University of Michigan. English Language Institute.; University of Michigan--Students.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cambodia.; Education.; Laos.; Photographs.; Thailand.; University of Michigan. English Language Institute.; University of Michigan--Students.; Vietnam.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Adams, James P. (James Pickwell), 1895-1969.; Anthony, Edward Mason, 1922-; Dana, Samuel Trask, 1883-1978; Deming, Olcott Hawthorne, 1909-; Eggertsen, Claude A. (Claude Andrew), 1909-; Forsythe, Warren Ellsworth, 1885-1960.; Fries, Charles C. (Charles Carpenter), 1887-1967; Gale, Esson M. (Esson McDowell), 1884-1964; Graf, Otto G.; Hopkins, Louis Allen.; Keniston, Hayward, b. 1883.; Kraus, Edward Henry, 1875-1973; Kurath, Hans, 1891-1992.; Lado, Robert, 1915-1995; Luther, George Edwin.; Marckwardt, Albert Henry, 1903-1975.; Marquardt, William F.; Pike, Kenneth L. (Kenneth Lee), 1912-2000; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Sawyer, Ralph A. (Ralph Alanson), 1895-1978.; Schaadt, Leonard A.; Shiel, Francis C.; Traver, Aileen.; Tuttle, Mildred L.; Yoakum, Clarence Stone, 1879-1945.
- Correspondence 1941-1957
  The Correspondence series (1941-1957, 4 linear ft.) is mostly arranged topically and then chronologically within each folder. Corespondents include: James P. Adams, Edward M. Anthony, Samuel T. Dana, Olcott T. Deming, Claude A. Eggertsen, Warren E. Forsythe, Esson M. Gale, Otto G. Graf, Hayward Keniston, Hans Kurath, Albert H. Marckwardt, William F. Marquardt, Ralph A Sawyer, Leonard A. Schaadt, Yao Shen, Francis C. Shiel, Aileen Traver, Mildred L. Tuttle, and Clarence S. Yoakum.
  - "A" General Correspondence (Box 1)
    (1-1)
  - Addresses of students for 1941 (Box 1)
    (1-2)
  - Advisors to Foreign Students (Box 1)
    (1-3)
  - American Express Co. (Box 1)
    (1-4)
  - American Council of Learned Societies (Box 1)
    (1-5)
  - Aviation Intern Course; Civil Aeronautics Administration 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    (1-6)
  - "B" General Correspondence (Box 1)
    (1-7)
  - Background Materials for the ELI Program 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    (1-8, 1-9, 1-10, 1-11)
  - Braun and Brumfield publishers (Box 1)
    (1-12)
  - Brumfield and Brumfield publishers (Box 1)
    (1-13)
  - Bucknell University (Box 1)
    (1-14)
  - Business Office, University of Michigan (Box 1)
    (1-15)
  - "C" General Correspondence (Box 1)
    (1-16)
  - Cooligan, Francis (Box 1)
    (1-17)
  - Conference Notes 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    (1-18)
  - Copyright (Box 1)
    (1-19)
  - Courses in English (other universities) (Box 1)
    (1-20)
  - "D" General Correspondence (Box 1)
    (1-21)
  - Dana, Dean S.T. (Box 1)
    (1-22)
  - Deming, Olcott H. (Box 1)
    (1-23)
  - "E" General Correspondence (Box 1)
    (1-24)
  - Employment Available for Teachers (Box 1)
    (1-25)
  - English 70-Advanced English as second language (Box 1)
    (1-26)
  - English Language Institute in Mexico-research (Box 1)
    (1-27)
  - Executive Committee Minutes (scattered) (Box 1)
    (1-28)
  - "F" General Correspondence (Box 1)
    (1-29)
  - Financial-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (1-30)
  - Ford Foundation (Box 1)
    (1-31)
  - Ford Motor Company Trips (Box 1)
    (1-32)
  - Fourth of July Outings-Olivet and Plymouth, Mich. (Box 1)
    (1-33)
  - "G" General Correspondence (Box 1)
    (1-34)
  - "H" General Correspondence (Box 1)
    (1-35)
  - Health Service (Box 1)
    (1-36)
  - Hindi File (Box 1)
    (1-37)
  - Housing (Box 1)
    (1-38)
  - "I" General Correspondence (Box 1)
    (1-39)
  - Institute of International Educations-Students at UM (Box 1)
    (1-40)
  - IIE-Teacher Trainees (Box 1)
    (1-41)
  - Inquiries-General (Box 1)
    (1-42, 1-43, 1-44)
  - Inquiries Concerning Institute from other universities (Box 1)
    (1-45)
  - Inquiries, Student 1946 (Box 1)
    (1-46)
  - Institute of Inter-American Affairs 1942-1946 (Box 1)
    (1-47)
  - Institute of Inter-American Affairs 1947 (Box 1)
    (1-48)
  - Institute of International Education (Box 2)
    (2-1)
  - Intensive Course in English, Inquiries
    - 1942 (Box 2)
      (2-2)
    - 1943-1944 (Box 2)
      (2-3)
    - 1945 (Box 2)
      (2-4)
    - 1947 (Box 2)
      (2-5)
    - 1948 (Box 2)
      (2-6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin American Students, Inquiries (Box 2)
    (2-7)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin American Students, Orders (Box 2)
    (2-8)
  - Inter-American Committee, University of Michigan (Box 2)
    (2-9)
  - Inter-American Demonstration Center Project (Box 2)
    (2-10)
  - Inter-American Educational Foundation, David Campa (Box 2)
    (2-11)
  - Inter-American Educational Foundation, Kenneth Holland (Box 2)
    (2-12)
  - Inter-American Educational Foundation, Willfred Mauck (Box 2)
    (2-13)
  - Inter-American Educational Foundation, Clifford Prater (Box 2)
    (2-14)
  - Inter-American Schools Service (Box 2)
    (2-15)
  - International Center, University of Michigan (Box 2)
    (2-16)
  - "J" General Correspondence (Box 2)
    (2-17)
  - Japanese Fulbright (Box 2)
    (2-18)
  - "K" General Correspondence (Box 2)
    (2-19)
  - W.K. Kellogg Foundation 1945-1950 (Box 2)
    (2-20)
  - W.K. Kellogg Foundation 1951-1955 (Box 2)
    (2-21)
  - Keniston, Hayward (Box 2)
    (2-22)
  - Kurath, Hans (Box 2)
    (2-23)
  - "L" General Correspondence (Box 2)
    (2-24)
  - Linguistic Institute-General Correspondence 1945 (Box 2)
    (2-25)
  - Linguistic Institute, Budget and Program 1945 (Box 2)
    (2-26)
  - Linguistic Institute, Possible Students and Inquiries 1945 (Box 2)
    (2-27)
  - Linguistic Institute, Possible Students and Inquiries 1946 (Box 3)
    (3-1)
  - Linguistic Institute, Possible Students and Inquiries 1947 (Box 3)
    (3-2)
  - "M" General Correspondence (Box 3)
    (3-3)
  - Marckwardt, Albert H. (Box 3)
    (3-4)
  - "N" General Correspondence (Box 3)
    (3-5)
  - National Association of Foreign Student Advisers 1953 (Box 3)
    (3-6)
  - National Association of Foreign Student Advisers 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    (3-7)
  - Negro Problem Bibliography (Box 3)
    (3-8)
  - "O" General Correspondence (Box 3)
    (3-9)
  - Office Equipment (Box 3)
    (3-10)
  - Organization of the English Language Institute (Box 3)
    (3-11)
  - Other English Language Institutes or Programs (Box 3)
    (3-12)
  - "P" General Correspondence (Box 3)
    (3-13)
  - Personnel, Forms, Procedures (Box 3)
    (3-14)
  - Publications (Box 3)
    (3-15)
  - "R" General Correspondence (Box 3)
    (3-16)
  - Recreational Activities for English Language Institute Students (Box 3)
    (3-17)
  - Requests for Teaching Materials and Publications 1943-1949 (Box 3)
    (3-18)
  - Requests for Teaching Materials and Publications 1950-1954 (Box 3)
    (3-19)
  - Requests for Teaching Materials and Publications 1955-1957 (Box 3)
    (3-20)
  - Revision: Quizzes (Box 3)
    (3-21)
  - Rockefeller Agents in Latin America 1942 (Box 3)
    (3-22)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, William Berrien (Box 3)
    (3-23)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, Hugo Muench (Box 3)
    (3-24)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, David H. Stevens (Box 3)
    (3-25)
  - "S" General Correspondence (Box 4)
    (4-1)
  - Sawyer, Ralph A.: Dean of the Graduate School (Box 4)
    (4-2)
  - Schaadt, Leonard: Business Manager of Resident Halls (Box 4)
    (4-3)
  - Scholarship Awards 1942-1943 (Box 4)
    (4-4)
  - Scholarship Awards 1945-1946 (Box 4)
    (4-5)
  - Speeches, Farewell Banquets (Box 4)
    (4-6, 4-7)
  - Staff Meeting Notes 1942-1943 (Box 4)
    (4-8)
  - Staff Meeting Notes 1944-1945 (Box 4)
    (4-9)
  - Staff Meeting Notes 1946-1950 (Box 4)
    (4-10)
  - Staff Meeting Notes 1951-1955 (Box 4)
    (4-11)
  - Students, Prospective 1942 (Box 4)
    (4-12)
  - Students, Prospective 1946-1947 (Box 4)
    (4-13)
  - Students, Prospective 1948 (Box 4)
    (4-14)
  - Students, Rejected (Box 4)
    (4-15)
  - "T" General Correspondence (Box 4)
    (4-16)
  - Teacher Trainees, Summer Sessions 1954-1955 (Box 4)
    (4-17)
  - Teacher Trainees, Summer Sessions 1956 (Box 4)
    (4-18)
  - Television Program Mail (The Search) (Box 4)
    (4-19)
  - "U" General Correspondence (Box 4)
    (4-20)
  - U.S. Office of Education, Thomas Cotner (Box 4)
    (4-21)
  - "V" General Correspondence (Box 4)
    (4-22)
  - Visitors to the Institute (Box 4)
    (4-23, 4-24, 4-25)
  - "W" General Correspondence (Box 4)
    (4-26)
  - Yoakum, Dean Clarence S. (Box 4)
    (4-27)
- C.C. Fries Correspondence 1940-1957
  The C.C. Fries Correspondence series (1940-1957, 1 linear ft.) contains the correspondence of ELI founder and director, Charles Carpenter Fries. Files are arranged chronologically and include both ingoing and outgoing correspondence.
  - 1940 (Box 5)
    (5-1)
  - 1941 (Box 5)
    (5-2)
  - February-July 1942 (Box 5)
    (5-3)
  - August-December 1942 (Box 5)
    (5-4)
  - January-April 1943 (Box 5)
    (5-5)
  - May-July 1943 (Box 5)
    (5-6)
  - August-October 1943 (Box 5)
    (5-7)
  - November-December 1943 (Box 5)
    (5-8)
  - January-February 1944 (Box 5)
    (5-9)
  - March-April 1944 (Box 5)
    (5-10)
  - May 1944 (Box 5)
    (5-11)
  - June 1944 (Box 5)
    (5-12)
  - July 1944 (Box 5)
    (5-13)
  - August-September 1944 (Box 5)
    (5-14)
  - October-November 1944 (Box 5)
    (5-15)
  - December 1944 (Box 5)
    (5-16)
  - January 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-17)
  - February 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-18)
  - March 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-19)
  - April 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-20)
  - May-June 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-21)
  - July-August 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-22)
  - September 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-23)
  - October 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-24)
  - November 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-25)
  - December 1945 (Box 5)
    (5-26)
  - January-February 1946 (Box 5)
    (5-27)
  - March 1946 (Box 5)
    (5-28)
  - April 1946 (Box 5)
    (5-29)
  - May 1946 (Box 5)
    (5-30)
  - June 1946 (Box 5)
    (5-31)
  - July 1946 (Box 5)
    (5-32)
  - August-October 1946 (Box 5)
    (5-33)
  - November-December 1946 (Box 5)
    (5-34)
  - January 1947 (Box 5)
    (5-35)
  - February-April 1947 (Box 5)
    (5-36)
  - May-June 1947 (Box 5)
    (5-37)
  - July-September 1947 (Box 5)
    (5-38)
  - October-December 1947 (Box 5)
    (5-39)
  - January-March 1948 (Box 5)
    (5-40)
  - April-December 1948 (Box 5)
    (5-41)
  - 1949 (Box 5)
    (5-42)
  - 1950 (Box 5)
    (5-43)
  - 1951 (Box 5)
    (5-44)
  - 1952 (Box 5)
    (5-45)
  - 1953 (Box 5)
    (5-46)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 5)
    (5-47)
  - Correspondence with and donations to the C.C. Fries Fund Committee 1957 (Box 5)
    (5-48, 5-49)
- Books 1944-1956
  The Books (1944-1956, 1 linear ft.) in the ELI records serve as English language teaching materials for Latin American and Chinese students, and also include Patterns of English Sentences and Lessons in Pronunciation.
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin-American Students, vol. I 1943 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin-American Students, vol. I 1947 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin-American Students, vol. II 1943 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin-American Students, vol. III 1943 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin-American Students, vol. IV 1943 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin-American Students, vol. V Index 1944 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin-American Students, vol. VI Supplement 1945 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin-American Students, vol. VI Supplement 1946 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin-American Students, vol. VI Supplement 1947 (Box 6)
  - Conversational English for Latin Americans in the United States, 1945 (Box 6)
  - Patterns of English Sentences, 1956 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Chinese Students, vol. I, pt. I 1946 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Chinese Students, vol. I, pt. II 1946 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Chinese Students, vol. II 1946 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Chinese Students, vol. III 1946 (Box 6)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Chinese Students, vol. IV 1946 (Box 6)
  - Lessons in Pronunciation, Part I 1948 (Box 6)
  - Lessons in Pronunciation, Part II 1948 (Box 6)
- Manuscripts of Publications undated
  The Manuscripts of Publications series (undated, .5 linear ft.) include several copies of An Intensive Course in English for Latin American Students
  - Intensive Course in English for Latin American students (Box 7)
  - Curso Intensivo en íngles para los estudeantes latinoamericános (Box 7)
  - An Intensive Course in English for Latin American Students, vol. VII, Teachers Supplement: Suggestions for Vocabulary Practice (Box 7)
- Scrapbooks 1941-1966
  The Scrapbooks series (1941-1966, .5 linear ft.) includes two scrapbooks with photographs.
  - Scrapbook and photograph album 1941-1946 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of Professor and Mrs. Leo Rockwell circa 1941-1966 (Box 7)
    (includes photographs)
- Project Files 1952-1976
  The Project Files (1952-1976, 2 linear ft.) contain various records of programs and projects run by the ELI. Examples include several overseas projects (SEAREP, Pakistan Project, etc.), the Robert Lado Project File, and the Teachers Education Project.
  - Robert Lado Project File 1952-1958 (Box 8)
  - Teachers Education Project 1952-1968
    - Program Material 1957 (Box 8)
    - Student Letters 1957 (Box 8)
    - Course Material 1962-1965 (Box 8)
    - ELI Project Programs 1952-1968 (Box 8)
  - Pakistan Project 1957-1963
    - Conference Material 1957 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence 1959-1963 (Box 8)
  - Ford-Japan Project 1958-1965
    - Correspondence 1958-1966 (Box 8)
    - Ford Foundation Proposals 1958-1959 (Box 8)
    - Progress Reports 1963-1964 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Reports 1959-1964 (Box 8)
    - Contracts 1964 (Box 8)
    - Final Reports 1965 (Box 8)
  - Peace Corps Program 1961-1964
    - Preparatory Material 1961 (Box 8)
    - Training Program in Thailand 1962 (Box 8)
    - Staffing and Appointments 1964 (Box 8)
    - Course Material 1964 (Box 8)
  - South East Asian Regional English Project (SEAREP) 1957-1965
    - Instructional Material 1958-1964
      - General Instructional Material (Box 8)
      - Burma Material 1959-1962 (Box 8)
      - Vietnam Material 1958-1959 (Box 8)
      - Thailand Material 1960 (Box 8)
      - Reading Lists 1960-1964 (Box 8)
    - Administrative Material 1958-1964
      - Procedural Information (Box 8)
      - Rice, Warner Correspondence 1958-1959 (Box 8)
      - Staffing Patterns 1958-1963 (Box 8)
      - Minutes 1958-1961 (Box 8)
      - Memoranda 1959-1964 (Box 8)
      - Newsletters 1959-1960 (Box 8)
      - Project Film 1959-1960 (Box 8)
      - Vehicle Insurance 1960-1961 (Box 8)
    - Reports 1958-1965
      - Annual Reports 1958-1963 (Box 8)
      - Annual Report Correspondence 1960-1965 (Box 8)
      - Semi-Annual Reports 1958-1963 (Box 8)
      - Monthly Reports 1959-1963 (Box 8)
      - Regional Conference Reports 1960 (Box 8)
      - Joint Committee Reports 1958-1959 (Box 8)
      - Audit Reports 1960-1965 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous Reports 1958-1962 (Box 8)
    - Contracts 1957-1964 (Box 9)
      - Contracts 1957 (Box 9)
      - Correspondence, re: Contracts 1958-1962 (Box 9)
      - Amendments to Contracts 1959-1963 (Box 9)
      - Contract Extension Material 1959-1964 (Box 9)
      - Contractor's Guide (Box 9)
    - Budgets 1957-1964
      - Allowances 1957-1960 (Box 9)
      - Budget organization 1958-1962 (Box 9)
  - South East Asian Regional English Project (SEAREP) 1957-1965 (cont.)
    - Budgets 1957-1964 (cont.)
      - Final Budgets
        - 1958-1959 (Box 9)
        - 1959-1960 (Box 9)
        - 1960-1961 (Box 9)
        - 1961-1962 (Box 9)
        - 1962-1963 (Box 9)
        - 1963-1964 (Box 9)
      - Projected Budgets
        - 1958-1959 (Box 9)
        - 1959-1960 (Box 9)
        - 1960-1961 (Box 9)
        - 1961-1962 (Box 9)
        - 1962-1963 (Box 9)
  - Program for Americans in Russia 1959 (Box 9)
  - Soviet Teachers Program 1966-1976
    - Preparation, Correspondence and Reports 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - Program Material 1967
      - Staff Appointments 1967 (Box 9)
      - Programs and Schedules 1967 (Box 9)
    - Program Material 1968
      - General Correspondence 1968 (Box 9)
      - Participants 1968 (Box 9)
      - Budget 1968 (Box 9)
    - Program Material 1969
      - General Correspondence 1969 (Box 9)
      - Participants 1969 (Box 9)
      - Staff Appointments 1969 (Box 9)
      - Budget and Related Correspondence 1969 (Box 9)
      - Course Material 1969 (Box 9)
      - Programs and Schedules 1969 (Box 9)
    - Program Material 1970
      - General Correspondence 1970 (Box 9)
      - Participants 1970 (Box 9)
      - Participant Correspondence 1970 (Box 9)
      - Staff Appointments 1970 (Box 9)
      - Budget 1970 (Box 9)
      - Course Material 1970 (Box 9)
      - Programs and Schedules 1970 (Box 9)
    - Program Material 1971
      - General Correspondence 1971 (Box 9)
      - Participants 1971 (Box 9)
      - Staff Appointments 1971 (Box 9)
      - Budget and Related Correspondence 1971 (Box 9)
      - Programs and Schedules (Box 9)
    - Correspondence and Tentative Budgets 1972-1976 (Box 9)
- Administrative Files 1952-2005
  The Administrative Files (1952-2005, 1.5 linear ft.) include records relating to the internal operation of ELI. The series contains a great deal of various meeting minutes, reports, agendas, and vision statements, and also represented are ELI anniversary celebrations, budgets, correspondence, and student statistics.
  - Advisory Committee-Policy Statements 1960-1961, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Anniversary (25th) 1966
    - Research Materials, Correspondence and Programs (Box 10)
    - Conference Papers (Box 10)
  - Anniversary (40th) 1981 (Box 10)
  - Anniversary (50th) 1991 (Box 10)
  - Annual Reports 2004-2005 (Box 10)
  - Audit Reports 1956 (Box 10)